<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<database name="Local_Config" title="OVS Local Configuration Database">
  <p>
    This database is for local configuration of an ovsdb-server. The
    database is meant to be unique, even among multiple clustered db
    servers, so that configuration that is local to that server can
    be configured separately (e.g. Connection information).
  </p>

  <table name="Config" title="ovsdb-server configuration">
    <p>
      The root local configuration table for an ovsdb-server. This table
      must have exactly one row.
    </p>
    <group title="Connection Options">
      <column name="connections">
        Database clients to which the Open vSwitch database server should
        connect or on which it should listen, along with options for how these
        connections should be configured.  See the <ref table="Connection"/>
        table for more information.
      </column>
    </group>
  </table>

  <table name="Connection" title="OVSDB client connections.">
    <p>
      Configuration for a database connection to an Open vSwitch database
      (OVSDB) client.
    </p>

    <p>
      This table primarily configures the Open vSwitch database server
      (<code>ovsdb-server</code>).
    </p>

    <p>
      The Open vSwitch database server can initiate and maintain active
      connections to remote clients.  It can also listen for database
      connections.
    </p>

    <group title="Core Features">
      <column name="target">
        <p>Connection methods for clients.</p>
        <p>
          The following connection methods are currently supported:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt>
            <code>ssl:<var>host</var></code>[<code>:<var>port</var></code>]
          </dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              The specified SSL/TLS <var>port</var> on the host at the given
              <var>host</var>, which can either be a DNS name (if built with
              unbound library) or an IP address. A valid SSL/TLS configuration
              must be provided when this form is used, this configuration can
              be specified via command-line options or the <ref table="SSL"/>
              table.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
            <p>
              SSL/TLS support is an optional feature that is not always
              built as part of Open vSwitch.
            </p>
          </dd>

          <dt>
            <code>tcp:<var>host</var></code>[<code>:<var>port</var></code>]
          </dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              The specified TCP <var>port</var> on the host at the given
              <var>host</var>, which can either be a DNS name (if built with
              unbound library) or an IP address.  If <var>host</var> is an IPv6
              address, wrap it in square brackets, e.g.
              <code>tcp:[::1]:6640</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt>
            <code>pssl:</code>[<var>port</var>][<code>:<var>host</var></code>]
          </dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              Listens for SSL/TLS connections on the specified TCP
              <var>port</var>.
              Specify 0 for <var>port</var> to have the kernel automatically
              choose an available port.  If <var>host</var>, which can either
              be a DNS name (if built with unbound library) or an IP address,
              is specified, then connections are restricted to the resolved or
              specified local IPaddress (either IPv4 or IPv6 address).  If
              <var>host</var> is an IPv6 address, wrap in square brackets,
              e.g. <code>pssl:6640:[::1]</code>.  If <var>host</var> is not
              specified then it listens only on IPv4 (but not IPv6) addresses.
              A valid SSL/TLS configuration must be provided when this form is
              used, this can be specified either via command-line options or
              the <ref table="SSL"/> table.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
            <p>
              SSL/TLS support is an optional feature that is not always built
              as part of Open vSwitch.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt>
            <code>ptcp:</code>[<var>port</var>][<code>:<var>host</var></code>]
          </dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              Listens for connections on the specified TCP <var>port</var>.
              Specify 0 for <var>port</var> to have the kernel automatically
              choose an available port.  If <var>host</var>, which can either
              be a DNS name (if built with unbound library) or an IP address,
              is specified, then connections are restricted to the resolved or
              specified local IP address (either IPv4 or IPv6 address).  If
              <var>host</var> is an IPv6 address, wrap it in square brackets,
              e.g. <code>ptcp:6640:[::1]</code>.  If <var>host</var> is not
              specified then it listens only on IPv4 addresses.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <p>When multiple clients are configured, the <ref column="target"/>
        values must be unique.  Duplicate <ref column="target"/> values yield
        unspecified results.</p>
      </column>

      <column name="read_only">
        <code>true</code> to restrict these connections to read-only
        transactions, <code>false</code> to allow them to modify the database.
      </column>

      <column name="role">
        String containing role name for this connection entry.
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Client Failure Detection and Handling">
      <column name="max_backoff">
        Maximum number of milliseconds to wait between connection attempts.
        Default is implementation-specific.
      </column>

      <column name="inactivity_probe">
        Maximum number of milliseconds of idle time on connection to the client
        before sending an inactivity probe message.  If Open vSwitch does not
        communicate with the client for the specified number of seconds, it
        will send a probe.  If a response is not received for the same
        additional amount of time, Open vSwitch assumes the connection has been
        broken and attempts to reconnect.  Default is implementation-specific.
        A value of 0 disables inactivity probes.
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Status">
      <p>
        Key-value pair of <ref column="is_connected"/> is always updated.
        Other key-value pairs in the status columns may be updated depends
        on the <ref column="target"/> type.
      </p>

      <p>
        When <ref column="target"/> specifies a connection method that
        listens for inbound connections (e.g. <code>ptcp:</code> or
        <code>punix:</code>), both <ref column="n_connections"/> and
        <ref column="is_connected"/> may also be updated while the
        remaining key-value pairs are omitted.
      </p>

      <p>
        On the other hand, when <ref column="target"/> specifies an
        outbound connection, all key-value pairs may be updated, except
        the above-mentioned two key-value pairs associated with inbound
        connection targets. They are omitted.
      </p>

    <column name="is_connected">
        <code>true</code> if currently connected to this client,
        <code>false</code> otherwise.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="last_error">
        A human-readable description of the last error on the connection
        to the manager; i.e. <code>strerror(errno)</code>.  This key
        will exist only if an error has occurred.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="state"
              type='{"type": "string", "enum": ["set", ["VOID", "BACKOFF",
                   "CONNECTING", "ACTIVE", "IDLE"]]}'>
        <p>
          The state of the connection to the manager:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt><code>VOID</code></dt>
          <dd>Connection is disabled.</dd>

          <dt><code>BACKOFF</code></dt>
          <dd>Attempting to reconnect at an increasing period.</dd>

          <dt><code>CONNECTING</code></dt>
          <dd>Attempting to connect.</dd>

          <dt><code>ACTIVE</code></dt>
          <dd>Connected, remote host responsive.</dd>

          <dt><code>IDLE</code></dt>
          <dd>Connection is idle.  Waiting for response to keep-alive.</dd>
        </dl>
        <p>
          These values may change in the future.  They are provided only for
          human consumption.
        </p>
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="sec_since_connect"
              type='{"type": "integer", "minInteger": 0}'>
        The amount of time since this client last successfully connected
        to the database (in seconds). Value is empty if client has never
        successfully been connected.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="sec_since_disconnect"
              type='{"type": "integer", "minInteger": 0}'>
        The amount of time since this client last disconnected from the
        database (in seconds). Value is empty if client has never
        disconnected.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="locks_held">
        Space-separated list of the names of OVSDB locks that the connection
        holds.  Omitted if the connection does not hold any locks.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="locks_waiting">
        Space-separated list of the names of OVSDB locks that the connection is
        currently waiting to acquire.  Omitted if the connection is not waiting
        for any locks.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="locks_lost">
        Space-separated list of the names of OVSDB locks that the connection
        has had stolen by another OVSDB client.  Omitted if no locks have been
        stolen from this connection.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="n_connections"
              type='{"type": "integer", "minInteger": 2}'>
        When <ref column="target"/> specifies a connection method that
        listens for inbound connections (e.g. <code>ptcp:</code> or
        <code>pssl:</code>) and more than one connection is actually active,
        the value is the number of active connections.  Otherwise, this
        key-value pair is omitted.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="bound_port" type='{"type": "integer"}'>
        When <ref column="target"/> is <code>ptcp:</code> or
        <code>pssl:</code>, this is the TCP port on which the OVSDB server is
        listening.  (This is particularly useful when <ref
        column="target"/> specifies a port of 0, allowing the kernel to
        choose any available port.)
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Connection Parameters">
      <column name="other_config" key="dscp"
              type='{"type": "integer"}'>
        The Differentiated Service Code Point (DSCP) is specified using 6 bits
        in the Type of Service (TOS) field in the IP header. DSCP provides a
        mechanism to classify the network traffic and provide Quality of
        Service (QoS) on IP networks.

        The DSCP value specified here is used when establishing the connection
        between the manager and the Open vSwitch.  If no value is specified, a
        default value of 48 is chosen.  Valid DSCP values must be in the range
        0 to 63.
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Configuration">
      External configuration options

      <column name="external_ids">
        External client-defined key-value pairs
      </column>
    </group>
  </table>
</database>
