<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<manpage program="ovn-northd" section="8" title="ovn-northd">
    <h1>Name</h1>
    <p>ovn-northd -- Open Virtual Network central control daemon</p>

    <h1>Synopsis</h1>
    <p><code>ovn-northd</code> [<var>options</var>]</p>

    <h1>Description</h1>
    <p>
      <code>ovn-northd</code> is a centralized daemon responsible for
      translating the high-level OVN configuration into logical
      configuration consumable by daemons such as
      <code>ovn-controller</code>.  It translates the logical network
      configuration in terms of conventional network concepts, taken
      from the OVN Northbound Database (see <code>ovn-nb</code>(5)),
      into logical datapath flows in the OVN Southbound Database (see
      <code>ovn-sb</code>(5)) below it.
    </p>

    <h1>Configuration</h1>
    <p>
      <code>ovn-northd</code> requires a connection to the Northbound
      and Southbound databases.  The default is <code>db.sock</code>
      in the local Open vSwitch's "run" directory.  This may be
      overridden with the following commands:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          <code>--ovnnb-db=<var>database</var></code>
        </p>
        <p>
          The database containing the OVN Northbound Database.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          <code>--ovsnb-db=<var>database</var></code>
        </p>
        <p>
          The database containing the OVN Southbound Database.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      The <var>database</var> argument must take one of the following forms:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          <code>ssl:<var>ip</var>:<var>port</var></code>
        </p>
        <p>
          The specified SSL <var>port</var> on the host at the given
          <var>ip</var>, which must be expressed as an IP address (not a DNS
          name) in IPv4 or IPv6 address format.  If <var>ip</var> is an IPv6
          address, then wrap <var>ip</var> with square brackets, e.g.:
          <code>ssl:[::1]:6640</code>.  The <code>--private-key</code>,
          <code>--certificate</code>, and <code>--ca-cert</code> options are
          mandatory when this form is used.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          <code>tcp:<var>ip</var>:<var>port</var></code>
        </p>
        <p>
          Connect to the given TCP <var>port</var> on <var>ip</var>, where
          <var>ip</var> can be IPv4 or IPv6 address. If <var>ip</var> is an
          IPv6 address, then wrap <var>ip</var> with square brackets, e.g.:
          <code>tcp:[::1]:6640</code>.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          <code>unix:<var>file</var></code>
        </p>
        <p>
          On POSIX, connect to the Unix domain server socket named
          <var>file</var>.
        </p>
        <p>
          On Windows, connect to a localhost TCP port whose value is written
          in <var>file</var>.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <h1>RUNTIME MANAGEMENT COMMANDS</h1>
    <p>
      <code>ovs-appctl</code> can send commands to a running
      <code>ovn-northd</code> process.  The currently supported commands
      are described below.
      <dl>
      <dt><code>exit</code></dt>
      <dd>
        Causes <code>ovn-northd</code> to gracefully terminate.
      </dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

</manpage>
