<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<manpage program="ovn-architecture" section="7" title="OVN Architecture">
  <h1>Name</h1>
  <p>ovn-architecture -- Open Virtual Network architecture</p>

  <h1>Description</h1>

  <p>
    OVN, the Open Virtual Network, is a system to support virtual network
    abstraction.  OVN complements the existing capabilities of OVS to add
    native support for virtual network abstractions, such as virtual L2 and L3
    overlays and security groups.  Services such as DHCP are also desirable
    features.  Just like OVS, OVN's design goal is to have a production-quality
    implementation that can operate at significant scale.
  </p>

  <p>
    An OVN deployment consists of several components:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        A <dfn>Cloud Management System</dfn> (<dfn>CMS</dfn>), which is
        OVN's ultimate client (via its users and administrators).  OVN
        integration requires installing a CMS-specific plugin and
        related software (see below).  OVN initially targets OpenStack
        as CMS.
      </p>

      <p>
        We generally speak of ``the'' CMS, but one can imagine scenarios in
        which multiple CMSes manage different parts of an OVN deployment.
      </p>
    </li>

    <li>
      An OVN Database physical or virtual node (or, eventually, cluster)
      installed in a central location.
    </li>

    <li>
      One or more (usually many) <dfn>hypervisors</dfn>.  Hypervisors must run
      Open vSwitch and implement the interface described in
      <code>IntegrationGuide.md</code> in the OVS source tree.  Any hypervisor
      platform supported by Open vSwitch is acceptable.
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
	Zero or more <dfn>gateways</dfn>.  A gateway extends a tunnel-based
	logical network into a physical network by bidirectionally forwarding
	packets between tunnels and a physical Ethernet port.  This allows
	non-virtualized machines to participate in logical networks.  A gateway
	may be a physical host, a virtual machine, or an ASIC-based hardware
	switch that supports the <code>vtep</code>(5) schema.  (Support for the
	latter will come later in OVN implementation.)
      </p>

      <p>
	Hypervisors and gateways are together called <dfn>transport node</dfn>
	or <dfn>chassis</dfn>.
      </p>
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    The diagram below shows how the major components of OVN and related
    software interact.  Starting at the top of the diagram, we have:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      The Cloud Management System, as defined above.
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
	The <dfn>OVN/CMS Plugin</dfn> is the component of the CMS that
	interfaces to OVN.  In OpenStack, this is a Neutron plugin.
	The plugin's main purpose is to translate the CMS's notion of logical
	network configuration, stored in the CMS's configuration database in a
	CMS-specific format, into an intermediate representation understood by
	OVN.
      </p>

      <p>
	This component is necessarily CMS-specific, so a new plugin needs to be
	developed for each CMS that is integrated with OVN.  All of the
	components below this one in the diagram are CMS-independent.
      </p>
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
	The <dfn>OVN Northbound Database</dfn> receives the intermediate
	representation of logical network configuration passed down by the
	OVN/CMS Plugin.  The database schema is meant to be ``impedance
	matched'' with the concepts used in a CMS, so that it directly supports
	notions of logical switches, routers, ACLs, and so on.  See
	<code>ovs-nb</code>(5) for details.
      </p>

      <p>
	The OVN Northbound Database has only two clients: the OVN/CMS Plugin
	above it and <code>ovn-nbd</code> below it.
      </p>
    </li>

    <li>
      <code>ovn-nbd</code>(8) connects to the OVN Northbound Database above it
      and the OVN Database below it.  It translates the logical network
      configuration in terms of conventional network concepts, taken from the
      OVN Northbound Database, into logical datapath flows in the OVN Database
      below it.
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
	The <dfn>OVN Database</dfn> is the center of the system.  Its clients
	are <code>ovn-nbd</code>(8) above it and <code>ovn-controller</code>(8)
	on every transport node below it.
      </p>

      <p>
	The OVN Database contains three kinds of data: <dfn>Physical
	Network</dfn> (PN) tables that specify how to reach hypervisor and
	other nodes, <dfn>Logical Network</dfn> (LN) tables that describe the
	logical network in terms of ``logical datapath flows,'' and
	<dfn>Binding</dfn> tables that link logical network components'
	locations to the physical network.  The hypervisors populate the PN and
	Binding tables, whereas <code>ovn-nbd</code>(8) populates the LN
	tables.
      </p>

      <p>
	OVN Database performance must scale with the number of transport nodes.
	This will likely require some work on <code>ovsdb-server</code>(1) as
	we encounter bottlenecks.  Clustering for availability may be needed.
      </p>
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    The remaining components are replicated onto each hypervisor:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      <code>ovn-controller</code>(8) is OVN's agent on each hypervisor and
      software gateway.  Northbound, it connects to the OVN Database to learn
      about OVN configuration and status and to populate the PN and <code>Bindings</code>
      tables with the hypervisor's status.  Southbound, it connects to
      <code>ovs-vswitchd</code>(8) as an OpenFlow controller, for control over
      network traffic, and to the local <code>ovsdb-server</code>(1) to allow
      it to monitor and control Open vSwitch configuration.
    </li>

    <li>
      <code>ovs-vswitchd</code>(8) and <code>ovsdb-server</code>(1) are
      conventional components of Open vSwitch.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <pre fixed="yes">
                                  CMS
                                   |
                                   |
                       +-----------|-----------+
                       |           |           |
                       |     OVN/CMS Plugin    |
                       |           |           |
                       |           |           |
                       |   OVN Northbound DB   |
                       |           |           |
                       |           |           |
                       |        ovn-nbd        |
                       |           |           |
                       +-----------|-----------+
                                   |
                                   |
                                +------+
                                |OVN DB|
                                +------+
                                   |
                                   |
                +------------------+------------------+
                |                  |                  |
 HV 1           |                  |    HV n          |
+---------------|---------------+  .  +---------------|---------------+
|               |               |  .  |               |               |
|        ovn-controller         |  .  |        ovn-controller         |
|         |          |          |  .  |         |          |          |
|         |          |          |     |         |          |          |
|  ovs-vswitchd   ovsdb-server  |     |  ovs-vswitchd   ovsdb-server  |
|                               |     |                               |
+-------------------------------+     +-------------------------------+
  </pre>

  <h2>Chassis Setup</h2>

  <p>
    Each chassis in an OVN deployment must be configured with an Open vSwitch
    bridge dedicated for OVN's use, called the <dfn>integration bridge</dfn>.
    System startup scripts create this bridge prior to starting
    <code>ovn-controller</code>.  The ports on the integration bridge include:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      On any chassis, tunnel ports that OVN uses to maintain logical network
      connectivity.  <code>ovn-controller</code> adds, updates, and removes
      these tunnel ports.
    </li>

    <li>
      On a hypervisor, any VIFs that are to be attached to logical networks.
      The hypervisor itself, or the integration between Open vSwitch and the
      hypervisor (described in <code>IntegrationGuide.md</code>) takes care of
      this.  (This is not part of OVN or new to OVN; this is pre-existing
      integration work that has already been done on hypervisors that support
      OVS.)
    </li>

    <li>
      On a gateway, the physical port used for logical network connectivity.
      System startup scripts add this port to the bridge prior to starting
      <code>ovn-controller</code>.  This can be a patch port to another bridge,
      instead of a physical port, in more sophisticated setups.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    Other ports should not be attached to the integration bridge.  In
    particular, physical ports attached to the underlay network (as opposed to
    gateway ports, which are physical ports attached to logical networks) must
    not be attached to the integration bridge.  Underlay physical ports should
    instead be attached to a separate Open vSwitch bridge (they need not be
    attached to any bridge at all, in fact).
  </p>

  <p>
    The integration bridge must be configured with failure mode ``secure'' to
    avoid switching packets between isolated logical networks before
    <code>ovn-controller</code> starts up.  See <code>Controller Failure
    Settings</code> in <code>ovs-vsctl</code>(8) for more information.
  </p>

  <p>
    The customary name for the integration bridge is <code>br-int</code>, but
    another name may be used.
  </p>

  <h2>Life Cycle of a VIF</h2>

  <p>
    Tables and their schemas presented in isolation are difficult to
    understand.  Here's an example.
  </p>

  <p>
    The steps in this example refer often to details of the OVN and OVN
    Northbound database schemas.  Please see <code>ovn</code>(5) and
    <code>ovn-nb</code>(5), respectively, for the full story on these
    databases.
  </p>

  <ol>
    <li>
      A VIF's life cycle begins when a CMS administrator creates a new VIF
      using the CMS user interface or API and adds it to a switch (one
      implemented by OVN as a logical switch).  The CMS updates its own
      configuration.  This includes associating unique, persistent identifier
      <var>vif-id</var> and Ethernet address <var>mac</var> with the VIF.
    </li>

    <li>
      The CMS plugin updates the OVN Northbound database to include the new
      VIF, by adding a row to the <code>Logical_Port</code> table.  In the new
      row, <code>name</code> is <var>vif-id</var>, <code>mac</code> is
      <var>mac</var>, <code>switch</code> points to the OVN logical switch's
      Logical_Switch record, and other columns are initialized appropriately.
    </li>

    <li>
      <code>ovs-nbd</code> receives the OVN Northbound database update.  In
      turn, it makes the corresponding updates to the OVN database, by adding
      rows to the OVN database <code>Pipeline</code> table to reflect the new
      port, e.g. add a flow to recognize that packets destined to the new
      port's MAC address should be delivered to it, and update the flow that
      delivers broadcast and multicast packets to include the new port.
    </li>

    <li>
      On every hypervisor, <code>ovn-controller</code> receives the
      <code>Pipeline</code> table updates that <code>ovs-nbd</code> made in the
      previous step.  As long as the VM that owns the VIF is powered off,
      <code>ovn-controller</code> cannot do much; it cannot, for example,
      arrange to send packets to or receive packets from the VIF, because the
      VIF does not actually exist anywhere.
    </li>

    <li>
      Eventually, a user powers on the VM that owns the VIF.  On the hypervisor
      where the VM is powered on, the integration between the hypervisor and
      Open vSwitch (described in <code>IntegrationGuide.md</code>) adds the VIF
      to the OVN integration bridge and stores <var>vif-id</var> in
      <code>external-ids</code>:<code>iface-id</code> to indicate that the
      interface is an instantiation of the new VIF.  (None of this code is new
      in OVN; this is pre-existing integration work that has already been done
      on hypervisors that support OVS.)
    </li>

    <li>
      On the hypervisor where the VM is powered on, <code>ovn-controller</code>
      notices <code>external-ids</code>:<code>iface-id</code> in the new
      Interface.  In response, it updates the local hypervisor's OpenFlow
      tables so that packets to and from the VIF are properly handled.
      Afterward, it updates the <code>Bindings</code> table in the OVN DB,
      adding a row that links the logical port from
      <code>external-ids</code>:<code>iface-id</code> to the hypervisor.
    </li>

    <li>
      Some CMS systems, including OpenStack, fully start a VM only when its
      networking is ready.  To support this, <code>ovn-nbd</code> notices the
      new row in the <code>Bindings</code> table, and pushes this upward by
      updating the <ref column="up" table="Logical_Port" db="OVN_NB"/> column
      in the OVN Northbound database's <ref table="Logical_Port" db="OVN_NB"/>
      table to indicate that the VIF is now up.  The CMS, if it uses this
      feature, can then react by allowing the VM's execution to proceed.
    </li>

    <li>
      On every hypervisor but the one where the VIF resides,
      <code>ovn-controller</code> notices the new row in the
      <code>Bindings</code> table.  This provides <code>ovn-controller</code>
      the physical location of the logical port, so each instance updates the
      OpenFlow tables of its switch (based on logical datapath flows in the OVN
      DB <code>Pipeline</code> table) so that packets to and from the VIF can
      be properly handled via tunnels.
    </li>

    <li>
      Eventually, a user powers off the VM that owns the VIF.  On the
      hypervisor where the VM was powered on, the VIF is deleted from the OVN
      integration bridge.
    </li>

    <li>
      On the hypervisor where the VM was powered on,
      <code>ovn-controller</code> notices that the VIF was deleted.  In
      response, it removes the logical port's row from the
      <code>Bindings</code> table.
    </li>

    <li>
      On every hypervisor, <code>ovn-controller</code> notices the row removed
      from the <code>Bindings</code> table.  This means that
      <code>ovn-controller</code> no longer knows the physical location of the
      logical port, so each instance updates its OpenFlow table to reflect
      that.
    </li>

    <li>
      Eventually, when the VIF (or its entire VM) is no longer needed by
      anyone, an administrator deletes the VIF using the CMS user interface or
      API.  The CMS updates its own configuration.
    </li>

    <li>
      The CMS plugin removes the VIF from the OVN Northbound database,
      by deleting its row in the <code>Logical_Port</code> table.
    </li>

    <li>
      <code>ovs-nbd</code> receives the OVN Northbound update and in turn
      updates the OVN database accordingly, by removing or updating the
      rows from the OVN database <code>Pipeline</code> table that were related
      to the now-destroyed VIF.
    </li>

    <li>
      On every hypervisor, <code>ovn-controller</code> receives the
      <code>Pipeline</code> table updates that <code>ovs-nbd</code> made in the
      previous step.  <code>ovn-controller</code> updates OpenFlow tables to
      reflect the update, although there may not be much to do, since the VIF
      had already become unreachable when it was removed from the
      <code>Bindings</code> table in a previous step.
    </li>
  </ol>

</manpage>
